Hi, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today is י"ג, Yud-Gimmel, the 12th. We're
in the middle of talking about the שירה shira of the לויים.
Levi'im.
And we pick up on the bottom of י"א עמוד ב'. Yud-Aleph
Amud-Bet. And we are talking about whether when you would do this.
The גמרא Gemara sort of starts by laying out the basic principle
is you do it by an עולת חובה olat chovah of the
ציבור, tzibur, which is basically the תמידים temidim and the מוספים. musafim.
But the question is whether you would do it by a communal
עולה olah that is free will. And the גמרא Gemara is trying
to prove it. So we pick up two lines in the wide
lines with a ברייתא braita which is going to be the focus
of our discussion for the rest of the day. So let's take
a look. Middle of the second line of the wide lines, י"א
עמוד ב'. Yud-Aleph Amud-Bet. תא שמע, Ta shma, come and hear.
ויוסי אומר מגלגלין זכות ליום זכאי וחובה ליום חייב. V'Yosei Omer, megalgelin
zechut l'yom zakai v'chovah l'yom chayav. So good things happen on meritorious
days and bad things on not meritorious days, on bad days. אמרו,
Amru, and here's the evidence of it, we're going to give only
the evidence for the second half of the sentence.
כשחרב בית המקדש בראשונה, K'shecharav Beit HaMikdash barishonah, when the first בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash was destroyed, אותו יום תשעה באב היה, oto yom
Tisha B'Av hayah, it was תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, which is the
day of the מרגלים meraglim that they came back and gave their
report. So that's not said here but that's presumably why it's originally
identified as a יום חייב. yom chayav. ומוצאי שבת היה, U'motzei Shabbat
hayah, it was Sunday. ומוצאי שביעית היה, U'motzei shevi'it hayah, and it
was the first year of the שמיטה shemitah cycle. Presumably those two,
Sunday and the first year of a שמיטה shemitah cycle, is not
about the יום חייב, yom chayav, although it does seem to have
something auspicious about it, like you know, like it was the end
of everything that preceded, it was the beginning of a new era,
of an era of גלות. galut. Anyway, that doesn't seem directly connected
though to יום חייב. yom chayav. ומשמרתו של יהויריב הייתה, U'mishmarto shel
Yehoyariv hayetah, and it was the cycle of יהויריב Yehoyariv in the
כהנים. kohanim. והיו כהנים ולויים עומדים על דוכנם, V'hayu kohanim u'Levi'im omdim
al duchanam, and the כהנים kohanim and the
לויים Levi'im were on their, you know, the דוכן, duchan, the platform.
It's a little funny because the כהנים, kohanim, were they really on
the דוכן? duchan? But okay, anyway. ואומרים שירה, V'omrim shirah, certainly, and
they would say, and they were singing their song.
Sounds like more like the לויים Levi'im that do this, you know.
I know, it really is the לויים Levi'im על דוכנם, al duchanam,
but okay.
Don't sing supposed to be the כהנים? kohanim?
Yeah,
anyway. ואומרים שירה, V'omrim shirah, what שירה shirah were they singing? So
it says, וישב עליהם את אונם וברעתם יצמיתם. Vayashov aleihem et onam
u'vera'atam yatzmitem. God will return upon them their iniquity, in their evil,
right. And the sixth day of Wednesday. The only problem is that
we just got through saying it was Sunday. Okay, and with the
evil he will cut them off. So you see that it was
like exactly the words came out of their mouth, those auspicious words.
ולא הספיקו לומר יצמיתם ה' אלוקינו, V'lo hispiku lomar yatzmitem Hashem Elokeinu,
they didn't get to the end of the פסוק pasuk עד שבאו
אויבים וכבשום, ad sheba'u oyvim v'kivshum, until that moment the enemies came
and conquered them in the first בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. וכן בשנייה,
V'chen bashniyah, and the exact same thing happened in the second בית
המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. It was תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, it was Sunday,
it was the first day of the שמיטה shemitah cycle. Not exactly
sure if we're also saying that they were singing that exact song.
The first day of the שמיטה shemitah cycle? ומוצאי שביעית Motzei shevi'it
is the first year.
That's right, you're right, you're right, it's not ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
you're right, obviously it's תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, thank you, thank you.
It was the first year of the שמיטה shemitah cycle, so you're
absolutely correct. Okay, so anyway now the גמרא Gemara goes on and
says like this. One minute. Okay, yeah, I'm just looking on the
thing, okay fine.
Okay, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. So it
was singing the שירה shirah of Wednesday although it was Sunday. So
the גמרא Gemara says, האי שירה מאי עבידתיה? hai shirah mai avidetei?
What was this שירה shirah doing? First of all, before we even
get to the question of the day of the week was wrong,
how could they have been saying שירה? shirah? When do you normally
say שירה? shirah? You say שירה shirah for the תמיד tamid or
for the מוסף. musaf. But it wasn't מוסף, musaf, it was תשעה
באב. Tisha B'Av. How about the תמיד? tamid? So it says, אילימא
דעולת חובה, ileima d'olat chovah, if it was the obligatory עולה, olah,
the תמיד, tamid, מי הוה? mi havah? Since when were they having
a תמיד tamid right on
תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av? בי"ז בתמוז בטל התמיד. B'Yud-Zayin B'Tammuz batel hatamid.
Already from the 17th of תמוז, Tammuz, they were no longer able
to bring the קרבן תמיד. korban tamid. That day, you know, that
they held, they didn't have so many animals available to them, they
were under siege. So one of the things we commemorate in י"ז
בתמוז Yud-Zayin B'Tammuz is they no longer brought the קרבן תמיד. korban
tamid. So what are they doing singing a שירה? shirah? There was
no קרבן תמיד korban tamid to be brought. אלא לאו, Ela lav,
it must have been דעולת נדבה, d'olat nedavah, that they happened to
have found one animal, they couldn't bring a תמיד tamid regularly, it
also maybe was a calf, not a sheep. So they did bring
an עולה, olah, and they were singing it for that. So you
see, it has them singing שירה shirah when there's no תמיד, tamid,
it must be a proof that you can say שירה shirah even
if it is a communal עולה olah even without being a fixed
obligatory עולה. olah. So the גמרא Gemara says, isn't that a proof?
So the גמרא Gemara says, ותסברא? v'tisbarah? Does that really make sense
that that's like what we need to assume
happened? מאי שנא דעולת חובה דלא הוה ומאי שנא דעולת נדבה דהוה?
Mai shena d'olat chovah d'lo havah, u'mai shena d'olat nedavah d'havah? So
first it says, if they weren't having a תמיד, tamid, how did
they have an animal to have a free-will עולה? olah? So the
גמרא Gemara says, so I already sort of mentioned that, הא לא
קשיא, ha lo kashya, that's not difficult. בן בקר קרי בעלמא הוא
דאיתרמי להו. Ben bakar krei b'alma hu d'isrami lehu. They maybe they
just found an animal, they didn't have enough to have a regular
תמיד, tamid, and it says, I think it specifically says בן בקר
ben bakar because if it was a calf, then you don't bring
a calf for your for your for your תמיד. tamid. Your תמיד
tamid is a sheep. Okay. So
anyway, the גמרא Gemara is saying that yeah, maybe it happened randomly
that they had it. But you see, even without a תמיד, tamid,
they're having a שירה. shira. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא,
Amar Rava, so is that a proof? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבא ואיתימא רב אשי ותסברא. Amar Rava v'isayma Rav Ashi v'tisbra.
Anyway, does that really make sense that that's what we have to
assume happened? First of all, שירה דיומא, shira d'yoma, the right שיר
shir of Sunday was לה' הארץ ומלואה, L'Hashem ha'aretz u'mlo'ah, right? That's
the Sunday שיר של יום. shir shel yom. וחדשה עליהם אסונם V'chadsha
aleihem asonam בשירי דארבע בשבתא הוא. b'shira d'arba b'shabta hu. That was
the Wednesday שירה shira that they were saying and you just got
through saying it was Sunday. אלא, Ella, so how do you even
explain that?
איילייא בעלמא הוא דנפל להו בפומייהו. Ailaya b'alma hu d'nafal lehu b'pumaihu.
Some type of a whale, a moan, not really, רש"י Rashi says
like a קינה. kina. What's the word for a קינה? kina? Dirge.
Dirge, yes, thank you, thank you. So it was just by pure
chance, things were not going the way they should have anyway, and
it was not what they should have been saying, but it just
so happened they got confused or whatever, they said something and it
was very auspicious. But it was not, does not prove that that's
what you do on a Sunday. Okay, but still why were they
saying שירה shira in the first place? So the גמרא Gemara says,
והא
איילייא בעלמא
V'ha ailaya
b'alma means like a dirge.
A dirge, yeah.
It just happened to be.
It happened to be, that was not right, they just happened to
come out, they accidentally were saying that, it wound up being very
auspicious, but whatever, it wasn't a real שירה. shira. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so it seems like that answer initially is that not
just like they accidentally said the wrong שירה, shira, but it sounds
like they weren't even singing a שיר של יום shir shel yom
at all. They were just maybe
anticipating the worst. So maybe they were singing it in explicit anticipation
of what was about to happen and it had nothing to do
with the normal שירה shira of the לויים. Levi'im. So they were
just lamenting what was about to happen. So the גמרא Gemara says,
you can't say that. והא עומדין על הדוכן קתני. V'ha omdin al
haduchan katani. It says they were standing on the דוכן, duchan, which
means that they were doing the official שירת לויים. shiras Levi'im. So
that's not a good answer. It might have been they made a
mistake, but they were still trying to do a שירה. shira. They
still tried to do the שירה shira of the קרבנות. korbanos. So
you still have to say how did they do the שירה shira
of the קרבנות korbanos without a תמיד? tamid? Let's finish this up.
So the גמרא Gemara says, כדרבי שמעון בן לקיש. K'de'Reish Lakish. All
right, so the answer is like what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says.
דאמר ריש לקיש, D'amar Reish Lakish, אומר שירה בלא קרבן. Omer shira
belo korban. ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says, you know, actually you're allowed
to say שירה shira anytime, the לויים, Levi'im, even not related to
a קרבן. korban.
As long as it's the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Right, as long as it's the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So
דחיובא d'chiyuva to say it with the תמיד, tamid, with the מוסף,
musaf, we even said before according to some you're not יוצא yotzei
although תוספות Tosafos limited that, that's where there's an obligation. But you
have a רשות reshus to say it at all times. And that's
what was happening. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, אי הכי,
Ei hachi, if that's true, בעולת נדבה נמי לימא. B'olas nedava nami
leima. So why do you have to ask a question, oh are
we, do we say it when you bring a, you know, an
עולת ציבור, olas tzibur, free will עולה? ola? Who cares if you're
obligated or not? You just got through saying you have the permission
to say it whenever you want. So say it then as well.
As long as when you have an עולת תמיד olas tamid you
do it then too, right?
What do you mean? ריש לקיש Reish Lakish said you can always
say it whenever you want. So the גמרא Gemara is saying, so
if that's and that's what was happening here when the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash was destroyed. So the גמרא Gemara says once we establish
you can say it whenever you want, who really cares whether you
have to say it if there's an עולת תמיד? olas tamid? If
in the end of the day you're allowed to say it, so
say it then also.
No, no, I know, but are we still saying that if you
have an עולת תמיד olas tamid you have to say it then,
and then any other time you can say it too?
You can say it whenever. So you could say the question is
whether you're חייב chayav to say it by an עולת נדבה. olas
nedava. No, but yeah, the הלכה halacha is you have to say
it by a תמיד tamid and a מוסף, musaf, and according to
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish you have a רשות reshus to say it
at all other times. Right. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says,
so if that's true just say it at this communal עולה, ola,
even a free will one. But it says no, נפקא דמיחרי חורבן.
Nafka d'meicharei churban. That we don't want to necessarily do because terrible
things will happen. What terrible things will happen? So it's not so
even clear. If I say it by a free will עולה, ola,
I'll say it by an obligatory עולה. ola. So what? I have
to say it. What's the bad thing? So רש"י Rashi says the
bad thing is that somehow when you say it by the free
will עולה, ola, you'll understand that it's only a רשות, reshus, it's
not an obligation. I don't know exactly how you'll understand that. And
then you'll start saying, oh, so in general when I say it
with an עולה ola it's a רשות, reshus, and you'll come to
and you'll come to not say it maybe. So therefore we would
rather not confuse it. If you're going to say it with an
עולה, ola, since when you say it with the עולת תמיד olas
tamid it's an obligation, if you're going to say it with an
עולת ציבור olas tzibur that's a, an עולת ציבור נדבה, olas tzibur
nedava, we also not to confuse it, we're only going to say
it if it's also an obligation. So yes, you have the permission
to say it at all times, but that still will not tell
us whether you should say it with an
עולת ציבור olas tzibur that's a רשות. reshus. So let's just read
the answer about this and then take Joey's question. מאי הוי עלה?
Mai havai alah? How did this whole thing wrap up? תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear, דתני רב מרי בריה דרב פנחס. d'tani
Rav Mari brei d'Rav Pinchas. So רב מרי Rav Mari teaches a
ברייתא braisa on the פסוק pasuk על עולותיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם. Al
olosaychem v'al zivchei shalmeychem. Again a פסוק pasuk by the חצוצרות, chatzotzros,
which we are just sort of merging with the idea of the
שירה shira of the לויים. Levi'im. Anyway, it says you do it
by your עולה ola and your שלמים. shlamim. So
he makes a... What type of שלמים Shlamim is
קדשי קדשים? Kodshei Kodashim? קדשים קלים Kodashim Kalim you eat them in
all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. No, it's קדשי קדשים Kodshei Kodashim in one
case, when you bring the two lambs by שבועות, Shavuot, those are
שלמי ציבור Shalmei Tzibur and they are קדשי קדשים. Kodshei Kodashim. So
that's limiting, not all שלמים, Shlamim, just those.
You see שבועות Shavuot then too when you bring that?
Yes, because we're now interpreting this also to be by קביעות. Kviut.
But now we reverse it, and now we learn back the other
way. ומה שלמים קבוע להם זמן, U-ma Shlamim kavua lahem zman, the
same way the two lambs of שבועות Shavuot have a fixed time,
they're a communal obligation with a fixed time, אף עולה קבוע לה
זמן, af Ola kavua la zman, even the עולה Ola is only
when it's not only communal, but communal with a fixed time. So
according to that ברייתא, Braita, you only do the שירה Shira when
you have a fixed communal עולה, Ola, a fixed time and obligation,
meaning תמיד Tamid and מוסף. Musaf. And now we have also ended
in the שלמים Shlamim for שבועות, Shavuot, and that seems to be
the times when you do it for the שירה, Shira, maybe also
for the חצוצרות, Chatzotzrot, the גמרא Gemara somewhat merging the two. Yes,
Charlie.
If I risk to distract, the traditional date for the destruction of
the First Temple, 3,338 years after the creation of the world, could
not have been the first year of the שמיטה. Shmita.
That's what we're going to be discussing in today's דף. Daf. Don't
worry. This ברייתא Braita that we just discussed is now going to
lead us into, if you thought we were done with calendars, we
might have been done with monthly calendars, but now we're onto yearly
calendars, and that is going to be the focus of today's דף.
Daf. So now that we've wrapped up דף י"ג עמוד ב', Daf
Yud Gimmel Amud Bet, we turn our attention to י"ד עמוד א',
Yud Dalet Amud Aleph, top of the דף. Daf. Okay, but first,
I should say first we have one more small issue to raise
by the שירה Shira and then we're going to get back to
this ברייתא. Braita. Let's take a look. איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, they
raised the question. נסכים הבאים בפני עצמן, Nesakhim ha-ba'im bifnei atzman, if
you bring the נסכים Nesakhim independently, טעונים שירה או אין טעונים שירה,
te'unim Shira o ein te'unim Shira, do you do שירה Shira or
not? What's the question? Do we say, כיון דאמר רבי שמואל בר
נחמני אמר רבי יונתן, keivan de-amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani amar Rabbi
Yonatan, מניין שאין אומרים שירה אלא על היין, minayin she-ein omrim Shira
ela al ha-yayin, the whole idea of saying it over the נסכים,
Nesakhim, why do we say it by the נסכים Nesakhim of the
עולה? Ola? Because of the concept of saying it over wine. So
therefore, even if it comes by itself, אמרינן, amrinan, we would say
it. או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say, אכילה ושתיה בעינן,
akhila u-shtiya be'inan, we only say it when it's wine with drink?
That's when maybe, you know, that's a really joyous time. So when
you have the wine with the קרבן, Korban, שתיה לחודיה, shtiya le-chudei,
wine by itself, maybe that's not as much about שמחה Simcha as
it is about just getting drunk. So anyway, somehow there's different symbolism,
so לא אמרינן, lo amrinan, we wouldn't say it. So do you
say it by wine by itself? Now what does it mean by
wine by itself? It sounds like it means that somebody makes a
נדבה Nedava to bring wine, which you're allowed to do, and you
pour the wine on המזבח ha-Mizbe'ach to bring נסכים. Nesakhim. The problem
with it is, for God's sakes, we just got through saying that
you only do it by a communal fixed עולה, Ola, right?
So here, why would I ask? Other things have נסכים, Nesakhim, but
no, no, no, you don't do it, you only do it with
a communal fixed עולה. Ola. So how could I think it's just
by נסכים Nesakhim which is private, free will, not fixed? So רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot both say that what we mean is, you're
allowed to bring the נסכים Nesakhim of a קרבן Korban the day
after or the night after or even multiple days after you bring
the קרבן. Korban. So the question is, let's say you did that.
You somehow got postponed, you didn't have enough wine or whatever it
was, you got distracted, and you're bringing the נסכים Nesakhim of Sunday's
קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid on Wednesday. So when you bring the נסכים
Nesakhim of Sunday's קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid on Wednesday, will you do
the שירה Shira with that wine when it's not linked to the
קרבן Korban which it came with?
Okay, and so you do Sunday's שירה Shira on Wednesday?
Ah, so which שירה Shira would you say? So the assumption is
you would say the שירה Shira of that day, not the שירה
Shira of the day that you're in. But it's not a חיוב
Chiyuv in, it's sort of like the whole question about if you
miss יעלה ויבא, Ya'aleh ve-Yavo, right? What happens if it's ראש חודש,
Rosh Chodesh, you have a ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh שיילה, shaila, it's
ראש חודש מנחה Rosh Chodesh Mincha and you forgot to say יעלה
ויבא Ya'aleh ve-Yavo and now it's מעריב Ma'ariv and it's not ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. You know what you do? You say two שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esrei even though the second one doesn't have יעלה ויבא
Ya'aleh ve-Yavo anyway, because the problem is not that you have a
חיוב Chiyuv to say X number of יעלה ויבאs. Ya'aleh ve-Yavo It's
a problem of the nature of the תפילה, Tefilla, the שמונה עשרה.
Shmoneh Esrei. So here too, the problem was not you missed Sunday
שירה. Shira. The problem was you did not have שירה Shira accompanying
this קרבן. Korban. So if it happens now to be Wednesday and
you're doing the יין Yayin for this, so you'll say the שירה
Shira of Wednesday. It doesn't matter which שירה Shira you say. Yes,
exactly, do it with the תמיד Tamid and you do it. So
that's the question. You're bringing the wine on a different day, do
you still say the שירה Shira for it? תא שמע, Ta shma,
come and hear. We're going to go back to this ברייתא. Braita.
רבי יוסי אומר מגלגלין זכות ליום זכאי, Rabbi Yosi omer megalgelin zkhut
le-yom zakai, etc., etc. So the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash was destroyed
on a Sunday, but they were happening to sing the שירה Shira
of Wednesday, right? האי שירה מאי עבידתיה? Hai Shira mai avidteih? What
is this
anyway, what's the context of saying this שירה? Shira? The same question
we asked before. אילימא דעולת חובה, Ilima de-olat chova, if it's the
תמיד Tamid שירה, Shira, מי הוה? mi hava? Since when were they
having a תמיד Tamid at that
time? בשבעה בתמוז בטל התמיד. Be-shiva be-Tammuz batul ha-Tamid. They already didn't
have a
תמיד Tamid from שבעה עשר בתמוז. Shiva Asar be-Tammuz. But according to
the last ברייתא baraita we ended up with, you don't say it
was an עולת נדבה. olat nedava. So how, what type of שירה
shira are they saying? אלא לאו דנסכין, Ela lav denisachin, it must
have been that it was not related to a קרבן, korban, it
was just נסכין, nesachim, and therefore they were singing the שירה shira
and that's the kind of שירה shira they're hearing. Now that's a
very strange answer because
if רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot are right, they're only talking about
נסכין nesachim that were postponed from the original קרבן, korban, so it
still begs the question: if you don't have תמיד tamid and you
don't have the original קרבן, korban, what are you doing it for?
Unless they're thinking that this is נסכין nesachim that was like six
months delayed from the time that they had a תמיד tamid before
תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, whatever, from the time that they had a
תמיד tamid before שבעה
עשר בתמוז.
Shiva
Asar B'Tammuz.
Somebody brought some wine.
Right. So it's three weeks delayed from the קרבן korban that they
brought before שבעה עשר בתמוז Shiva Asar B'Tammuz and now they're actually
bringing the wine because that day because they're trying to wrap that
up. Anyway, it's a funny היכי תימצי, heichi timtza, but the גמרא
Gemara rejects it anyway. The גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא ואיתימא רב
אשי, amar Rava ve'itayma Rav Ashi, ותסברא, ve'tisbara, does
that make sense that you think they're talking like about something exactly
formal and halakhic? First of all, שירה דיומא shira deyoma לה' הארץ
ומלואה, la'Hashem ha'aretz umelo'ah, the שירה shira of Sunday, which we said
it was, was לה' הארץ ומלואה. la'Hashem ha'aretz umelo'ah. וישב עליהם את
אונם, Ve'yashiv aleihem et onam, בשירה דארבע בשבת הוא. bishira de'arba beshabat
hu. They were saying the Wednesday שירה, shira, so the whole thing
was messed up anyway. So what does it mean? אלא איבה בעלמא
דאפנו בפומייהו. Ela eiva be'alma de'afnu bepumaihu.
So they were just singing a dirge, which again at this initial
stage the גמרא Gemara understands means that they weren't even doing it
as שירה, shira, they were just anticipating the חורבן churban and singing
a dirge. So the גמרא Gemara says, והא עומדין על דוכנן תניא?
veha omdin al duchnan tanya? It says they were standing on the
platform, which means it was a formal שירה. shira. So now we're
back to it. How were they, so maybe they made a mistake
and sang the wrong one, but they were still doing formal שירה.
shira. How were they doing formal שירה shira if they didn't have
the תמיד? tamid? So the גמרא's, Gemara and if you don't want
to say that it was related to the wine by itself, so
the גמרא Gemara says, כדריש לקיש, kide'Reish Lakish, like ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish, אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, אומרים שירה שלא על הקרבן,
omrim shira shelo al hakorban, that you say it even you have
a permission to say it whenever you want. So the גמרא Gemara
says, fine, shouldn't that answer our original point then? אי הכי, I
hachi, בנסכין נמי לימא? benesachim nami leima?
So even if you're not obligated to say it when the wine
comes by itself, at least you should have the allowance to say
it when the wine comes by itself. Now that we're saying that
the reason the לויים Levi'im were doing what they were doing on
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av was just they had the רשות. reshut. So
if you have רשות reshut to say שירה shira at all times,
say it by wine by itself. No, נפיק מיניה חורבא, nafik minei
churba, bad things will happen. What will be the bad things? So
again, as רש"י Rashi says, the Temple's destroyed. Right, yeah, there you
go. That's חורבא, churba, that's true, that is a חורבן. churban. Anyway,
the bad things will be that you'll come to associate שירה על
היין shira al yayin with רשות, reshut, somehow you'll know that it's
רשות, reshut, and that'll lead to not being
as scrupulous about it even when it's obligated. So anyway, we've rejected
this as relevant for our question. So we still don't, so what
do we conclude? We've concluded that regarding which קרבן korban you say
it with, only with a fixed communal עולה, olah, meaning basically תמיד
tamid and a מוסף, musaf, also maybe the שלמים shelamim on שבועות.
Shavuot. You say it during the pouring of the wine. Do you
say it by the wine by itself? Not really concluded, but what
we have learned is that you have the permission to really say
it, that's when you're obligated to say it, you have a permission
to say it at all times. And the interesting thing about the
at all times seems to be even at a period when they're
not pouring נסכין. nesachim. Even for a קרבן יחיד korban yachid or
any קרבן korban out there, they just want to stand there during
the middle of the day and do שירה, shira, which then gets
to the question of אין אומרים שירה אלא על היין, ein omrim
shira ela al hayayin, right, which we raised yesterday, is not an
absolute. It sort of might be the primary sort of or the
obligatory, but not that it's actually forbidden at other times. You know,
like we said, you can say קידוש kiddush on המוציא hamotzi if
you have to, and here the לויים Levi'im could do the שירה,
shira, at least they had the permission, not the obligation, to do
it at any time. Yes, Charlie.
They don't bring the possibility that maybe the particular שירים shirim of
the day were established at a later point?
Ah, no, they do not bring that possibility.
Which implies that they must consider the particular days to be very
ancient.
The גמרא Gemara definitely understands that that is correct. Yes.
Why couldn't they also see this whole thing as a premonition? That
they were standing there because they realized what was about to happen
and that's where they wanted to do their departure.
Well, that's I think the גמרא's Gemara first answer when it says
they were just singing a dirge. But then the גמרא Gemara says,
but you know, they wouldn't have done it on the platform.
That's what I mean, the whole thing as a premonition, that this
is where they were losing their responsibility that they would continue to
have. And then there's this מדרש midrash that the keys go up
and everything. I mean, this whole thing.
So you mean the fact that they're doing it wrong is just
an indication that things are in the process
of...
That's just the words they wanted to say because they realized this
whole thing was happening, this was...
Well, I do agree, but
that's what it says on the דוכן. duchan. Because this is where
they usually would have had their responsibility if they could keep it.
That's a nice point. So I think... So maybe you could say
that that's true and as long as the גמרא Gemara just doesn't
want to think that they were violating. Right. So once we've established
that they're allowed to say it, which was ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish
point whenever they want, then I think the framing you give could
exactly be why they were saying it. But the גמרא Gemara just
wants to, does not want to assume that they were actually in
violation when they were doing it. So it wants to say that
they were allowed. Okay, now we spend the rest of today's דף
daf working out the years and the calendar. So get ready. גופא.
Gufa. רבי יוסי אומר מגלגלין זכות ליום זכאי Rabbi Yosei omer: Megalgelin
zechut leyom zakai etc. בחורבן בית ראשון במוצאי שבת ובמוצאי שביעית. Bechurban
bayit rishon, bemotzaei Shabbat, uvemotsaei shevi'it. Now he said that it was
on the first month of a שמיטה shemita cycle. So the גמרא
Gemara says: מי משכחת לה? Mi mishkachat lei? Does that really work
out? That that's when the חורבן churban was? The first year, I
said month, I meant year. The first year of a שמיטה shemita
cycle? והא כתיב, Veha ketiv, the פסוק pasuk says: בעשרים וחמש שנה
לגלותנו. Be'esrim vechamesh shana legalutenu.
This is יחזקאל Yechezkel saying on the 25th year of our exile.
Now, now יחזקאל Yechezkel was not exiled with the חורבן הבית, churban
habayit, he was exiled with the, with the, with
the exile of יכניה. Yechanya. עם יכניה מלך יהודה. im Yechanya melech
Yehuda. Okay, anyway, so right, by, by, by Mordechai, by Esther, right.
Anyway,
so he was exiled with יכניה, Yechanya, which as we will see
was 11 years before the חורבן הבית. churban habayit. Okay, so he
is now saying in the 25th year of our, my, יחזקאל's Yechezkel
exile, which, look at the next part of the פסוק: pasuk: בראש
השנה בעשור לחודש. Berosh hashana be'asor lachodesh. On בראש השנה Rosh Hashana
on the 10th of the month. Obviously you're going to have, how
can you have בראש השנה Rosh Hashana on the 10th of the
month? We'll talk about that. בארבע עשרה שנה אחר אשר הכתה העיר.
Be'arba esre shana achar asher huketa ha'ir.
14 years after the city and the temple were destroyed. So the
25th year when we were exiled, which was 14 years after the
temple was destroyed. So their exile, the exile of יחזקאל Yechezkel with
יכניה Yechanya was 11 years before the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash was
destroyed. Okay. So what does this prove? How do we figure out
from here which year in the שמיטה shemita cycle it was? So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says: מחד בשבוע... Mi-chad
beshavua... so the גמרא, Gemara, I'm sorry, says: איזו היא שנה שראש
השנה בעשור לחודש? Eizehu shana she-Rosh Hashana be'asor lachodesh?
So what does it mean בראש השנה Rosh Hashana on the 10th
of the month? What year is בראש השנה Rosh Hashana on the
10th of the month? הוי אומר זה יובל. Hevei omer: Zeh yovel.
It's the יובל yovel year. Why? Because the גמרא Gemara understands, because
it says: What do you do on the יובל? yovel? בעשור לחודש
הזה תעבירו שופר בחודש השביעי בעשור לחודש ביום הכפורים תעבירו שופר בכל
ארצכם. Be'asor lachodesh hazeh, ta'aviru shofar bachodesh hashvi'i be'asor lachodesh, beyom hakippurim
ta'aviru shofar bechol artzechem. On יום כיפור Yom Kippur you blow the
שופר. shofar.
So the יום כיפור Yom Kippur of the יובל yovel serves as
a type of the really official beginning of the year. The גמרא
Gemara says, for example, that from ראש השנה Rosh Hashana until יום
כיפור Yom Kippur you could not work your slaves but they didn't
go free yet. So the jubilee year sort of had begun but
it wasn't yet official and didn't have all the impact until, until
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So therefore יום כיפור Yom Kippur is being
called a ראש השנה. Rosh Hashana. So this is important because now
this tells us that 14 years after the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
was destroyed was a יובל yovel year. Now, a יובל yovel year
is the first year of a שמיטה shemita cycle, right? Because it's
seven sevens, and the first year of a שמיטה shemita cycle is
a יובל yovel year. So now we know year 14 is a
יובל yovel year, is a year one of a שמיטה shemita cycle.
So now we're going to work back. Let me just sort of
show you, it makes it a little bit easier. So let's say
it's the 50th year. It's really not the 50th year, it's like
the first year. Yeah, but you might still count it just for,
you know, you can count 50 units or 49 years, but it
still doesn't matter. It's still the first year after a seven. So
here, if this is יובל, yovel, right, which is one, right, because
this is the end of seven sevens, right? Here, so you had
seven sevens, you had five others go back here, and that's יובל.
yovel. And this is when that פסוק pasuk was referring, right? Now
he says it is the 14th year from the time that it
was destroyed. But if it was destroyed on a year one, okay,
which is what we were saying, we were saying it was destroyed
on the first year of a cycle, and assuming you count the
endpoints, so assuming you count the endpoints, so from year one to
year one is eight years, right? And then to another year one,
right, is, what, right? Is, well, I mean, even if you go
one, two, three, four, five, six, seven, right? And now here's the
point, if you just count this, right, how many years? It's 14.
That's an easier way to say it, it's 14. But if you
count the endpoints, right, it's 15th year from the time it occurred,
assuming you're counting the endpoints. So that's going to be the גמרא's
Gemara question. The גמרא's Gemara going to assume you count the endpoints,
and therefore it's going to say: If it's true that it was
destroyed on a year one, it should call this the year 15,
not year 14. That's the question. The answer's going to be very
obvious, you just say we're not counting one of the endpoints. Okay,
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואי
סלקא דעתך בחד
בשבוע חרוב. Ve'isalka da'atach bechad beshavua charov. If it was destroyed on
the first of, it says שבוע shavua but it means a week,
it means a week of years. If it was destroyed on the
first of a שמיטה shemita cycle, מחד בשבוע לחד בשבוע תמני. mi-chad
beshavua lechad beshavua tamni.
So if you go from one of year one and you're counting
the endpoints, right, so from one to seven is seven, then on
the year one of the next cycle, year, in year eight, is
תמני. tamni. לחד בשבא אחרינא חמיסר L'chad b'shaba achrina chamisaser
and then you get to the next year one and then that's
seven more and then you're at fifteen. So I mean I just
showed you on the board, obviously 14 years and you counting both
the next year, you're counting both endpoints, you have 15. So it
would give you 15 הויא. havya. So how could the פסוק pasuk
say that it was on the 14th year of the חורבן, churban,
it should have said the 15th year of the חורבן? churban? Okay?
So אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, ארבע עשרה שנה אחר שנה שחרבה העיר.
arba asra shana achar shana shecharva ha'ir.
We're not counting the first endpoint. 14 years after year 14, meaning
not after year 14, yeah but I'd like to call it year
14 because that makes it clear like which when you're starting your
counting. So it's year 14 starting in the year after the חורבן,
churban, right? So if this is the חורבן, churban, right? That's the
חורבן, churban, so and this, you know, this year here of the
cycle is year one, so this is year 14 after the חורבן,
churban, okay? So as opposed to it's year 15 where the year
of the חורבן churban counts as year one. No, the year after
the חורבן churban is year one and therefore it's year 14. Okay,
fine. So that's we can make it work. So the גמרא Gemara
said, אי הכי, ee hachi,
if that's true, בעשרים וחמש שנה, b'esrim v'chamesh shana, how can you
say that it was 25 years after their exile? עשרים ושית הויא,
esrim v'shis havya, it was 26 years after their exile. How do
we know? Because if יחזקאל Yechezkel is saying that this year, right,
and he's calling this year 14, right, that's what he's calling it,
and he says it's also year 14 from the חורבן churban and
he says it's year 25 from his exile, יחזקאל's Yechezkel exile, okay,
which basically means that when was יחזקאל Yechezkel exiled? Right, 11 years,
right, before there was 11 before the חורבן, churban, right, because you're
going to add 11 before, so he was exiled 11 years before
the חורבן. churban. So now let's see whether that actually
works. So let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this,
it really according to that that we're skipping the year of the
חורבן, churban, so you're not going to get 25, you'll get 26
because you're basically not counting the year of the חורבן. churban.
And we know, not confusingly, you know, forget what year it was.
All right, so let's take a look. It says, דאמר מר, d'amar
mar, how do we know that where's this problem come from? Because
we've taught, גלו בשבע גלו בשמונה. galu b'sheva galu b'shmona. They were
exiled in year seven and year eight. גלו בי"ח גלו בי"ט. galu
b'yud chet galu b'yud tet. They were exiled in year 18 and
year 19. Now what does this mean? Seven and eight are really
the same year, it depends on what you're counting from. Are you
counting
from the from the from the what do you call it? From
the exile, not the exile, from the conquering of, are you counting
from the, excuse me, ascendancy of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar to his throne, or
from the fact in the second year that נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar was on
his throne, he actually sort of subjugated, he didn't send them to
exile, but he subjugated what's his name, not יכניה Yechanya but the
other one, יהויקים. Yehoyakim. So, okay, oh, yeah, I always make the
mistake, it wasn't יכניה, Yechanya, it was יהויכין. Yehoyachin. I don't know,
I was thinking about the מגילה, Megilla, I'm sorry, I get the
two names confused. So anyway, so this year one here is the
exile of, you know what I'm going to do it a little
bit shorter, not to scale, so you can see it. Okay, so
this is the 11 years. This is גלות יהויכין, galut Yehoyachin, which
is, which is יחזקאל, Yechezkel, okay? So therefore he says 11 years,
so it was 14 years after the חורבן, churban, which is
25 years, right, 25 years from the time he was exiled. Now
we are going to say that there were two exiles. There was
this exile, right, and there was the חורבן churban exile, okay, right?
Here we're saying separated by 11 years. All right, so but we're
saying this exile occurred in year 7, 8 and this exile occurred
in year 18, 19. Okay, so what do we mean 7, 8?
Because it was eight years from the ascendancy of, here this is
going to be eight years, here is where נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar becomes king,
okay, so it's eight
years, it was the eighth year since he was king, and in
year two of נבוכדנצר's Nevuchadnezzar becoming king, this was כיבוש יהויקים, kibush
Yehoyakim, that when when the earlier, like when יהויקים Yehoyakim basically rebelled
against נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar came and he basically subjugated him again,
he didn't send him into exile, but he was subjugated. So this
year is 7, 8, meaning it's eight since נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, seven from
כיבוש יהויקים, kibush Yehoyakim, and this year of the חורבן churban is
18, 19. Okay,
so this shows anyway, let's take a look, wait a second.
So your year two, you mean like one year after he was
king, right?
Not two years of נבוכדנצר... Nevuchadnezzar... yeah, this is year one of
נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. Okay, so again I've made a mistake, it's not יכניה,
Yechanya, it's יהויכין. Yehoyachin. So for those who caught... anyway, why is
this an issue? Because... This basically says, this is assuming we're talking
about not again how many years gap there is, but we're talking
about which year if you're doing a counting system: year one, year
two, year three. So here's the point. It's very clear that it
doesn't matter. Let's just look at the 7-18, let's look at the
8-19. So if this were called year one, what would year 18
be called?
No, it's a trick. It's always off by one, right? It's year
12, right? Because you're counting both endpoints, correct? So if this shows
us that if this is year one, this is year 12. Now
we said that counting after the חורבן, Churban, you have 14 years.
Counting after the חורבן, Churban, you have 14 years to 26. And
that's the bottom. If we said the 14 was counting the year
of the חורבן, Churban, then it makes sense. We have 12, but
we can't count that year of the חורבן Churban twice. So we're
only going to count now 13 years and get 25. But if
this gets us through the year of the חורבן Churban and then
we start the 14 after, we're going to get 26. So that's
the גמרא's Gemara's problem. Based on this, we see that the חורבן
Churban occurred on year 12.
And if you're starting your year counting of your 14 years not
the year of the חורבן, Churban, which allows you to subtract one,
but the year after the חורבן, Churban, so you add 14 to
12, you get 26. Let's take a look in the Artscroll. What?
Nice table in the Artscroll. So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. The גמרא Gemara says, let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara says like this: משבע ועד
תמני סרי, mishva ve'ad tamnei srei, from seven until 18, חד סרי
chad srei is 11 years. But meaning there's an 11-year gap, that's
not counting that as the endpoint, but now we're going to have
to count that for the next cycle. וחמש סרי, vechamesh srei, and
then you add 15 from the year of the חורבן Churban until
the year יחזקאל Yechezkel was talking about, because now you're saying that's
15 years, so אשתכח דעשרין ושית, ishtakach de'asrin veshit, it's 26.
So that's as I said, just put the year endpoint at the
other side. Anyway, now you've got a problem because basically it's saying
like this: I would have said that the חורבן Churban occurred on
year two of the cycle, of the שמיטה Shmita cycle, and year
14 means not 14 after but year 14. Then it would have
been 11 plus 14 and it would have been 25. But you're
saying actually that it occurred on year one and that it's 14
years after. So basically you're adding a year, right? You're saying it's
not the 14th year of the חורבן, Churban, 14th year after, you're
adding a year, that's going to get us to 26, not to
25. אמר לך רבינא, amar lach Ravina, so רבינא Ravina says back,
ולדידך, uledidach, and according to you, מי ניחא, mi nicha, why do
you think it's good? I just explained why it's good, but מכדי,
michdi, I'm going to show you it's not good. Let's take a
look. גלו נמי בתשע סרי. galu nami betsha srei. This is very
bizarre that although this is clearly right and this is in the
way that he says it, so don't worry about it, we're going
to get there. But anyway, clearly, but he actually thinks that we're
not describing one גלות galut here, 18-19 depends on the counting. We're
saying that there were two גליות. galuyot. There's a גלות galut on
year 18 and another גלות galut on year 19. Now since we
have a year when גלות galut a year
before the חורבן הבית, Churban HaBayit, but you have to understand things
by context. So he's going to say if you read it that
way and you really believe that there was the year 19 גלות
galut and that was the real חורבן בית המקדש, Churban Beit HaMikdash,
anyway, it's going to give you an extra year. It's going to
throw everything off by a year. It's not going to be 25,
it's going to be 26. Because now you're saying from the time
that יחזקאל Yechezkel was נגלה, nigleh, it wasn't year 12, you're saying
it's now year 13.
It depends which one he was גולה goleh in.
Right. Anyway, let's take a look. He just says he thinks that
19 means it was really a year later was the real גלות.
galut. He says anyway, if the real גלות galut was a year
later, you're anyway going to have a problem regardless. He says like
this: מכדי גלו נמי בתשע סרי. michdi galu nami betsha srei. They
were נגלה nigleh on 19. משבע עד תשע סרי, mishva ad tsha
srei, so you can't do seven to 18, you have to do
seven to 19. תרי סרי, trei srei, that gets you 12 years,
again not counting the last year as the endpoint. Then
וארבע סרי, ve'arba srei, you say that when the 14 is not
14 after the חורבן Churban but according to the חורבן. Churban. Fine,
but you're still going to get 12 plus 14. אשתכח דעשרין ושית,
ishtakach de'asrin veshit, it's 26. He's reading 19 as a separate year,
as a different year, says you're anyway going to be off by
one. אלא מאי אית לך למימר, ela mai it lach lemeimar, so
what's your answer to that? לבר משתא דגלו
בה. levar mishta degalu bah. You're not going to include the year
of the actual exile itself. ולדידי
נמי לבר משתא דגלו בה, uledidi nami levar mishta degalu bah, I
too won't include the year of the exile itself. What does he
mean? What's the answer? The answer is basically like this: this חורבן
Churban year is not, when יחזקאל Yechezkel says year 25, that חורבן
Churban year is not counted in either counting. When he counts how
many years from his exile to the חורבן, Churban, right, so it
occurred in year 12, but it was really only a gap of
11 years. Exactly. And then there was a gap of 11 years.
Sorry I did it this way. So and then after the חורבן
churban till he was talking was a space of, right, 14 years.
So that's when he says 25. Now of course it's funny because
from one point to the next is 26. But he's doing is
he's cutting out the חורבן. churban. From here till the חורבן, churban,
not including the חורבן, churban, is 11. After the חורבן churban till
here is 14. 25. The חורבן churban year didn't happen. Okay, not
that it didn't happen, but
we're not counting it.
So that's how he says, ah, so I can still get 25.
I can still say that it occurred on מוצאי שביעית motzei shevi'is
and I'm still going to get 25 years because we're not counting
the חורבן churban in either sort of segment.
But the thing is he doesn't say that. Like the תוספתא Tosefta
says,
שמונה לגלותנו. shemona l'galutenu. So he doesn't divide it anyway. Right. After
the חורבן. churban.
So the גמרא Gemara says what?
After the חורבן. churban.
You know, I mean from the siege until the חורבן churban was
three weeks and then that's it. I mean it felt like it
lasted a year. I think the פסוקים pesukim don't ever really spell
out like what the aftermath was. Right. Anyway, let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. So מכל מקום שית סרי לבינה קשיא. m'kol makom shesh
esre l'binah kasha. So okay, but what are you going to do
now? You claim actually that there was a גלות galus in year
19. So now you're still stuck with another year. You sort of
had cut out the חורבן churban from the middle, but that was
still working with the 18 number. Your now your whole question, your
whole challenge was claimed on an idea that there was a separate
חורבן churban in 19. The גמרא Gemara says now the גמרא Gemara
admits that the 19 was like a red herring. מי סברת שלש
גליות הויין? Mi savrat shalosh galuyos havyan? No. There really wasn't a
חורבן churban in like 7, 18, and 19. There wasn't a separate
חורבן churban in 19.
18/19 was the way of designating the same year. So גלו בשבע
לכיבוש יהויקים. galu b'sheva l'kibush Yehoyakim. It was year 7 from the
time יהויקים Yehoyakim was conquered by, you know, by
נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. שהיא שמונה לנבוכדנצר. she-hi shemona l'Nevuchadnezzar. So there's one year
called 7/8. It was 7 years from the time יהויקים Yehoyakim was
conquered, 8 years from the time נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar became king. The second
year of נבוכדנצר's Nevuchadnezzar kingship he reigned, he conquered יהויקים. Yehoyakim. So
therefore the גלות galus of יהויכין Yehoyachin with יחזקאל Yechezkel was year
7/8. And גלו בשמונה עשרה לכיבוש יהויקים שהיא תשע עשרה לנבוכדנצר. galu
b'shmone esre l'kibush Yehoyakim she-hi tsha esre l'Nevuchadnezzar. And the year of
חורבן בית המקדש churban Beis HaMikdash was year 18/19. Year 18 from
the time that יהויקים Yehoyakim was conquered and year 19 of נבוכדנצר's
Nevuchadnezzar reign. דאמר מר, D'amar mar, because we've taught, שנה ראשונה כיבש
נינוה. shana rishona kibesh Ninveh. The first year of נבוכדנצר's Nevuchadnezzar reign
he conquered נינוה. Ninveh. שניה עלה וכיבש יהויקים. shniya ala v'kibesh Yehoyakim.
The second year of his reign he conquered יהויקים. Yehoyakim. So anyway,
all of this was to explain what? All of this was to
explain that we said the חורבן churban happened here on the first
year of a שמיטה shemita cycle. יחזקאל Yechezkel says
that
he was talking on a, excuse me, first year of a שמיטה
shemita cycle. He was talking on a first year when it was
year 14. So we say year 14 does not mean count the
חורבן churban as year 1. That would make it year 15. Year
14 means 14 years after the year of the חורבן. churban. Ah,
there were 11 years before. So it would be 11, 1, and
14 should get you 26. And he said it was year 25.
And the basic answer is don't count the חורבן churban year at
all. 11 years before the חורבן, churban, 14 years after, not counting
the חורבן, churban, you get 25. And this allows us to continue
to claim that the חורבן churban happened the first year of the
שמיטה shemita cycle. Yes.
Yeah, in that case if either their שמיטה shemita year is incorrect,
our שמיטה shemita year is incorrect, or we missed some...
Well, this is only בית ראשון Bayis Rishon anyway. So let's keep
on reading because we are so not done. So the גמרא Gemara
says okay. So that was the first בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Now
we're going to the remainder of this ברייתא. braisa. וכן בשניה. V'chen
b'shniya. Same is true of the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So
the גמרא Gemara says ושניה במוצאי שביעית מי משתכחא לה? v'shniya b'motzei
shevi'is mi mishtachas lah? So since when
was the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash destroyed on a, on the
first year of a cycle? אמכדי, Amachdi, let's take a look. בית
שני כמה קם? Bayis sheni kama kam? How long was the second
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash around? Now there's a huge difference between what
happens if you ask the גמרא Gemara or you ask a historian.
If you ask a historian, I think it's like what, 580 years,
70 years, something like that? Second בית המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash?
586 or 7 plus 70, so yeah, 600 and it's a long
time.
Right. Well, no, not plus 70.
How long was it around for?
How long was it around?
Oh, 516 years
plus or minus a year. Okay, fine. Right. So but anyway according
to the גמרא Gemara it was 410, 420. So how long was
the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash around? 420 years. ארבע מאות ועשרים.
Arba me'os v'esrim. So now, how do they get that? Now, so
okay, that's just a מסורה. mesorah. We're not going to worry about
that now. But we're going to say it was a מוצאי שמיטה.
motzei shemita. Now we're going to assume that they began counting the
שמיטה shemita as soon as they returned. Okay, so as soon as
they built the, not returned, but as soon as they built the
בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. That's what we're going to assume. So now,
how are you going to get from 420 years
to
a מוצאי שמיטה? motzei shemita? Anyway, you even if you didn't assume
you started it anew, you could say there were seventy years between
the two, so that's ten cycles, so it's going to get you
to the same thing anyway. Right. So let's take a look now
what the גמרא Gemara says. So, okay, so okay, so גמרא Gemara
says, ארבע מאה תמני יובלי. Arba me'ah tmanei yovlei. Now here's the
thing though, and why you can't just count by
sevens, because we're counting by every time there's a יובל, yovel, it's
not included in the regular cycle. So they're units of fifty. They're
not units of, as it were, it's not all by sevens. You
have to count by units of fifty.
What you mean by that is like after the יובל, yovel, then
it's year one. So it's not like seven, seven, seven, seven, it's
forty-nine, fifty, then one.
Seven, יובל, yovel, one. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so this
really is not just sort of ascribing it to the seventy anyway.
There's a general assumption חורבן הבית churban habayis they stopped the whole
cycle. So they rebuilt the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, started the cycle
again. So, so how much, how many יובלים yovels do you have
in four hundred years? תמני יובלי. tmanei yovlei. Eight יובלים. yovels. Eight
times fifty is four hundred. So ארבעסרי, arbassrei, now you're left with
תרי שבועי. trei shavu'ei. So then take out two cycles of fourteen
years, four hundred and twenty, you're left with six years. Okay. So,
פשו להו שש, pashu lehu shesh, you're left with six years. So
it's not occurring, the חורבן churban is occurring in the sixth year
of a cycle, not in the first year of a cycle. הוו
ליה בשישא בשבוע, havu lei beshisa beshavu'a, it's in the sixth year
of a cycle. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא מני, ha mani,
no, who is this go like? רבי יהודה היא, Rabbi Yehuda hi,
דאמר de'amar שנת חמישים עולה לכאן ולכאן. shnas chamishim oleh lekan ulekan.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that the שמיטה shmittah year is not
a, the יובל yovel year, excuse me, is not independent. The יובל
yovel year is year one of the next cycle. עולה לכאן ולכאן,
oleh lekan ulekan, it's year fifty of the previous cycle and year
one of the next. So according to him, you could just do
a big divide by seven. You don't have to worry about יובל
yovel years. And seven divided by four hundred and twenty gets you
sixty. Thank
you. So, אתי, asi, so now the גמרא Gemara doesn't just doing
that, sort of works based on the יובל yovel factor we did.
Because we said there are eight יובלים. yovels. So according to him,
if there are eight יובלים, yovels, we had those, he would actually
have eight extra years out of those יובלים, yovels, right? We sort
of said four hundred is eight יובלים. yovels. גמרא Gemara says, oh,
according to him, you have those יובלים yovels count towards an extra
year. You basically gives you eight extra years.
So, אייתי תמני, ayisi tmanei, תמני, tmanei, so you
have eight extra years that we were counting as יובל yovel years,
he would count those. So you have eight extra years and we
have said that it was in, from our computation, it was year
six. והני שש, vehani shesh, so eight plus six, six, הוי ארבעסרי,
havei arbassrei, fourteen, אשתכח מוצאי שביעית חרב. ishtakach motza'ei shevi'is charav. That
gets you onto year one of a שמיטה shmittah cycle. So we
would have just done the math easier. We would have just said
four hundred and twenty divided by seven equals sixty. Fine. So it
has a perfect number of cycles without the יובל yovel and it
happens on מוצאי שמיטה. motza'ei shmittah. גמרא Gemara says, one minute, אי
רבי יהודה, ei Rabbi Yehuda, if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, בראשונה
לא משכחת ליה. berishona lo mishkachas lei. It's not going to
then it won't work out for the first בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Why won't it work out for the first בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash?
Because דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, שבע עשרה יובלות
מנו ישראל משנכנסו לארץ ועד שיצאו. shva esrei yovlot manu Yisrael mishenichsu
la'aretz ve'ad sheyatz'u. There were seventeen יובלות yovlot from the time they
entered into the land until they actually left the land. Now, assuming
that is assuming that a יובל yovel is fifty years. Fifty times
seventeen is, anybody? Eight hundred and fifty. Okay. So, והא, veha, now
partly I'll tell you, I'll tell you very quickly where the גמרא
Gemara gets this number from. Because the גמרא Gemara says, because the
פסוק pasuk says that they built the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash by
שלמה, Shlomo, it says that they built it in year four hundred
and eighty from יציאת מצרים. yetzias Mitzrayim. So that means that it
was year four hundred and forty from the time they came into
the land. The second, first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash was around four
hundred and ten years, and therefore four hundred and forty plus four
hundred and ten is eight hundred and fifty. So eight hundred and
fifty years from the time they built the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
till it was destroyed. Now, if you'll remember, we
just said, first one, talking first, first one, okay? Four hundred and
forty years till they built it, right, sorry, four hundred and forty
years till they built it from the time they entered ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and four hundred and ten years it was around, it
was around eight hundred, I did it again, it was destroyed in
year eight hundred and fifty from the time they entered into ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now, if you're, which is seventeen יובלות. yovlot. Now
if you'll remember, we just said on עמוד א amud aleph that
it was destroyed, that it was destroyed on, you know, two cycles,
right, out, I mean that this was the יובל, yovel, fourteen years
afterwards was the יובל.
yovel. So it doesn't work.
How do we say it was a perfect number of יובלות, yovlot,
right, we actually said that they were fourteen years minus.
So let's take a look. So the answer is anybody's number 14
mean anything to people? Exactly. That works out now. Ah.
So, okay, now משנכנסו לארץ עד שיצאו. Mishenichnesu l'aretz ad sheyatzu. Okay.
So there, well we'll read it in the גמרא. Gemara. There were
so 17,
850 years משנכנסו לארץ mishenichnesu l'aretz from the time they entered the
land עד שיצאו ad sheyatzu until the
חורבן. Churban. ואי אתה יכול לומר V'ee ata yachol lomar משעה שנכנסו
מנו. misha'ah shenichnesu manu. You can't really say they began counting the
יובל Yovel cycles. So it's true it's 850 years, but not really
17 cycles. They didn't really begin counting the cycles from the minute
they
entered it. שאם אתה אומר כן She'im ata omer kein נמצא בית
המקדש חרב בתחילת יובל. nimtza Beis HaMikdash charev b'techilas Yovel. Because then
it's exactly 17 perfect cycles and the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash would
be destroyed at the beginning of a יובל. Yovel. ואי אתה מוצא
V'ee ata motzei and then it doesn't work with the פסוק pasuk
we just quoted on the עמוד א' Amud Aleph which was בארבע
עשרה שנה אחר שהוכתה העיר b'arba esreh shanah achar shehuksa ha'ir that
it only 14 years after was a יובל. Yovel. So how are
you going to work it? 850 years, but then we find out
that 14 years later was a יובל. Yovel. So it must be
they didn't start counting until year 14, until they were there for
14 years. Right? If they'd start counting immediately, it would have been
יובל Yovel when it was destroyed. But it wasn't יובל Yovel till
14 years later. So you have to assume everything has a 14-year
shift. So they didn't start counting till they were there 14 years.
How does that work?
אלא צא מהם שבע שכבשו ושבע שחלקו. Ela tzei meihem sheva shekavshu
v'sheva shechilku. As Dov correctly guessed, there were seven years of conquering
the land, seven years of dividing it between the tribes. And until
the land was actually in their possession and divided according to the
tribes, it was not really considered conquered and considered full ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. And therefore, they did not start counting the יובלים Yovels
until after they were there 14 years. And that's why it was
exactly 850 years they were there, but the יובל Yovel occurred only
14 years after the חורבן. Churban. Okay. ואי V'ee now, that works
out perfectly assuming that a יובל Yovel is year 50 and it
does not and you're doing 50-year cycles, not 49-year cycles. But ואי
רבי יהודה, v'ee Rabbi Yehuda, but if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
right, now he's got a problem.
איכא שבסרי משבסרי יובלי. Ika shivsrei mishivsrei yovlei. You have 17 years
now leftover from 17 יובלים, Yovels, right, because he wasn't counting them
as part of the cycle. שדי הני Shadi hanei and now you
have to, you know, add those back as it were. הוו להו
בתלתא בשבוע. Havu lehu b'tlata b'shavua. And now we've got a problem.
I mean, actually two problems. Number one is that then clearly year
14 isn't going to be a יובל Yovel year, which the גמרא
Gemara isn't even pointing out, but that's obvious, right, because this only
works perfectly if you have 50-year cycles. And problem number two is
that then you have 17 extra years, so your שמיטה Shmita cycle
is three years later. And we went to all this trouble to
say שמיטה Shmita was year one of the שמיטה Shmita cycle. Now
you'll be on a year, you know, four of the שמיטה Shmita
cycle. So the whole thing is messed up if it's רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So how can you say, here's again the problem. The
second part of the ברייתא Baraisa said that the same thing happened
in the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, which meant it was
year one of the cycle. The only way we're able to get
the second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to be year one of the
cycle is if we assume רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that there were
49-year cycles. But the only way we're able to get the first
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash to be year one of the cycle is
if we assume that there are 50-year cycles. So you can't make
it work. The first part of the ברייתא Baraisa assumes 50-year cycles,
the second part assumes 49-year cycles.
Is there a different starting point for the first?
So that's interesting. So the רמב"ם, Rambam, I should say, actually thinks
that whether you count the יובל Yovel year as part of the
cycle or not shifted between the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and
the second. Not because it was a shift of פסק, psak, but
actually it had to do it related to issues about whether they
had יובל, Yovel, whether they were מקדש יובל mekadesh Yovel in the
second בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or not, because they didn't have all
the requirements for יובל Yovel in the second בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So actually, that might be an interesting answer. Maybe it was 50-year
cycles and then it was 49-year cycles. But the גמרא Gemara here
does not think that. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says הנהו שני דאגלינהו סנחריב עד דאתי
ירמיהו ואהדרינהו לא קחשיב להו. Hanehu shani d'aglinhu Sancheriv ad d'asi Yirmiyahu
v'ahadrinhu lo kachashiv lehu. The גמרא Gemara actually says no, no, no.
There was a hiatus of and therefore in the first בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and that's how remember there was basically 17 years here
that was messing us up, right, because of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
you have 17 extra years that was getting it all out of
sync. The גמרא Gemara says there was a period they didn't count
the years of the cycle. What was that period? It was when
סנחריב Sancheriv came and, you know, destroyed ישראל, Yisrael, not יהודה, Yehuda,
and sent the ten tribes into exile. So the הלכה halacha is
that יובל Yovel doesn't apply unless you have all of the inhabitants
there. So the גמרא Gemara then has another place where it has
a מדרש Midrash which basically says that in the time of יאשיהו
Yoshiyahu many, many years later, it says you remember the famous story
that יאשיהו Yoshiyahu found the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, etc. Anyway, he calls חולדה הנביאה Chulda HaNeviah and
he doesn't call ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. So the גמרא Gemara says well where
was ירמיהו? Yirmiyahu? So the גמרא Gemara says oh, he was on
a he was on a mission. What was his mission? He was
going to get the ten tribes and bring them back to
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So the גמרא Gemara understands that that during
that period until he did this mission, they weren't in the middle
they weren't counting the cycle. And only when he restored them did
they get back to starting the cycle again. And according and it's
actually not a hiatus,
actually
says... But if you do from the time of the finding of
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in יאשיהו Yoshiyahu till the חורבן Churban
and you start it, that is going to get you an exact
number of an exact number of שמיטות, Shmitas, so that'll be year
one of the חורבן Churban and it'll be 14 years shy of
the יובל. Yovel. So רש"י Rashi does the math, but basically what
the גמרא Gemara is saying is, oh, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda it all gets mixed up because it's 49 not 50. Don't
worry, basically we started counting new at the time of יאשיהו Yoshiyahu
when ירמיהו Yirmeyahu did this mission, and once we started counting new,
that then will work out perfectly that it was 14 years before
the end of יובל Yovel when the חורבן Churban occurred. Okay.
Is there scriptural proof he did that?
What? From scripture? No, no, no, it's all based on a דרש.
Drash. Okay, so that's answer number one, the גמרא Gemara says. איבעית
אימא Iba'is eima or answer number two, לעולם רבנן, Le'olam Rabbanan, it
really is the Rabbis' 50-year cycle. So 50-year cycle, how do you
say in the second בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it occurred in, no,
no, no, 50-year cycle solves the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but
then how does the ברייתא Braisa say in the second בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash it was year one of a cycle? We just proved
that that can't be, that it would be year six. וכי תנא
וכן בשניה, V'chi tana v'chen bashniya, when the ברייתא Braisa says, oh,
the same thing happened in the second בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, אשערה,
Ashara, it doesn't mean exactly the same thing. It means it was
תשעה באב, Tisha B'av, it means that maybe it was Sunday, but
we don't mean everything was exactly the same and it was not
year one of the cycle. That you're right, that was not the
case. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that makes sense. אילו לא
תימא הכי, Ilu lo teima hachi, because it really can't have been
the exact same. Exact same would have meant what we said, that
it was the cycle of יהויריב Yehoyariv and they were singing the
wrong song. So the גמרא Gemara says that couldn't have happened in
the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Why not? Let's take a look.
משמרתו של יהויריב בשניה מי הוה? Mishmarto shel Yehoyariv bashniya mi hava?
When, since when was there the watch, the cycle of יהויריב, Yehoyariv,
right, these are one of the 24 כהנים Kohanim families? Since when
did that happen in the second בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Why not?
I mean, they had כהנים, Kohanim, they had משמרות, Mishmaros, they had
לויים, Levi'im, but they didn't have יהויריב. Yehoyariv. Why not? והתניא, Vehatanya,
we taught in a ברייתא, Braisa, ארבע משמרות עלו מן הגולה, Arba
mishmaros alu min hagola, of the 24 משמרות Mishmaros of the כהנים,
Kohanim, only four returned from the exile. Right, if you read עזרא
נחמיה, Ezra Nechemya, they're having a real hard time getting the Jews
to leave גלות Galus where it's, you know, the Golden מדינה, Medina,
and to come back to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So only four
of the משמרות Mishmaros came back. Which were the four? ידעיה וחריים
פשחור ואימר. Yedaya vecharim Pashchur ve'imar. Okay. עמדו נביאים שביניהם, Amdu nevi'im
shebeineihem, the prophets among them, there weren't many prophets left by then,
but חגי זכריה מלאכי, Chaggai Zecharya Malachi, וחילקום לעשרים וארבע משמרות. Vechilkum
l'esrim ve'arba mishmaros. They wanted to keep the institution of 24 משמרות,
Mishmaros, so they said, fine, you four families are going to now,
you know, represent the 24 משמרות. Mishmaros. How does that work? בללום
ונתנו בקלפי, Bilulum venasnu bekalfi, they basically wrote out little slips of
paper of the 24 משמרות, Mishmaros, put them all in a jar.
בא ידעיה, Ba Yedaya, so ידעיה Yedaya came ונטל חלקו, Venatal chelko,
he picked his piece. How did he exactly get his name? רש"י
Rashi said that was like a miracle. Okay, but anyway, he picked
the first slip. Look at that, it was his name. But then
וחלק חברו שש, Vechalech chavero sheish, and then he picked five other
slips and which represented, and those were, you know, five of the
other בתי כהונה Batei kehuna that had not returned, and now his
family is going to represent those בתי כהונה. Batei kehuna. וחריים ונטל
חלקו וחלק חברו שש וכן פשחור וכן אימר. Vecharim venatal chelko vechelko
chavero sheish vechen Pashchur vechen Imar. So now each one of those
families stands in for themselves and for five other families. והתקינו נביאים
שביניהם, Vehitkinu nevi'im shebeineihem, and now they established שאפילו יהויריב ראש משמרות
עולה, She'afilu Yehoyariv rosh mishmaros oleh, let's say now all of a
sudden, oh, now it's a lot better, now יהויריב Yehoyariv is coming
back to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael 100 years later, and not only
that, the head of the משמרות Mishmaros is here, it's his week
and he wants to serve. Tough luck, you weren't here when it
really mattered, so לא ידחה ידעיה ממקומו. Lo yidacheh Yedaya mimkomo. ידעיה
Yedaya is now יהויריב. Yehoyariv. You might be, you know, whatever, born
from יהויריב, Yehoyariv, but you have lost your rights. ידעיה Yedaya is
now יהויריב. Yehoyariv. אלא ידעיה עיקר ויהויריב טפל. Ella Yedaya ikar veyoyariv
tafel. They're the ones that are big, maybe you can do some
assisting them, but they are now יהויריב, Yehoyariv, you're no longer יהויריב.
Yehoyariv. So anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says this proves what? It
proves that it couldn't have been exactly like the first בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, because the first בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash we said it
was the משמר Mishmar of יהויריב, Yehoyariv, and now we're saying there
was no משמר Mishmar of יהויריב. Yehoyariv. Of course, maybe it meant
exactly that, that since they represented יהויריב, Yehoyariv, it was משמר Mishmar
that was standing in for יהויריב, Yehoyariv, but the גמרא Gemara understands
that it means it literally, so they're saying, look, it wasn't exactly
like the first בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, so אלא אשערה, Ella ashara,
in many ways it was similar to the first בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, not exactly. So maybe the לויים Levi'im made the wrong same
mistake with their song, but it wasn't the משמר Mishmar of יהויריב,
Yehoyariv, and similarly it wasn't the first year of a שמיטה Shmita
cycle, maybe it was the sixth year of the שמיטה Shmita cycle.
Okay, that is it for today.